What is Kafka?
Apache Kafka is a distributed publish-subscribe messaging system and a robust queue that can
handle a high volume of data and enables you to pass messages from one end-point to another. Kafka is suitable for both offline and online message consumption. Kafka messages are persisted on the disk and replicated within the cluster to prevent data loss. Kafka is built on top  of the ZooKeeper synchronization service. It integrates very well with Apache Storm and Spark
for real-time streaming data analysis.
Benefits
Following are a few benefits of Kafka −
"Reliability − Kafka is distributed, partitioned, replicated and fault tolerance."
Scalability − Kafka messaging system scales easily without down time..
Durability − Kafka uses Distributed commit log which means messages persist on disk as
"fast as possible, hence it is durable.."
Performance − Kafka has high throughput for both publishing and subscribing messages. It
maintains stable performance even though many TB of messages are stored.
Kafka is very fast and guarantees zero downtime and zero data loss.
Use Cases
Kafka can be used in many Use Cases. Some of them are listed below −
Metrics − Kafka is often used for operational monitoring data. This involves aggregating
statistics from distributed applications to produce centralized feeds of operational data.
Log Aggregation Solution − Kafka can be used across an organization to collect logs
from multiple services and make them available in a standard format to multiple con-sumers.
Stream Processing − Popular frameworks such as Storm and Spark Streaming read data
"from a topic, process it, and write processed data to a new topic where it becomes available for"
users and applications. Kafka’s strong durability is also very useful in the context of stream
processing.
Need for Kafka
Kafka is a unified platform for handling all the real-time data feeds. Kafka supports low latency
"message delivery and gives guarantee for fault tolerance in the presence of machine failures. It has the ability to handle a large number of diverse consumers. Kafka is very fast, performs 2 million writes/sec. Kafka persists all data to the disk, which essentially means that all the writes go to the page cache of the OS (RAM). This makes it very efficient to transfer data from page"
cache to a network socket.
Apache Kafka - Fundamentals
"Before moving deep into Kafka, you must be aware of the main terminologies such as topics,"
"brokers, producers and consumers. The following diagram illustrates the main terminologies and the table describes the diagram components in detail."
Fundamentals
"In the above diagram, a topic is configured into three partitions. Partition 1 has two offset factors"
"0 and 1. Partition 2 has four offset factors 0, 1, 2, and 3. Partition 3 has one offset factor 0. The id of the replica is the same as the id of the server that hosts it."
"Assume, if the replication factor of the topic is set to 3, then Kafka will create 3 identical replicas"
"of each partition and place them in the cluster to make available for all its operations. To balance a load in a cluster, each broker stores one or more of those partitions. Multiple producers and consumers can publish and retrieve messages at the same time."
1) Topics
"A stream of messages belonging to a particular category is called a topic. Data is stored in topics.Topics are split into partitions. For each topic, Kafka keeps a minimum of one partition. Each such partition contains messages in an immutable ordered sequence. A partition is"
implemented as a set of segment files of equal sizes.
2) Partition
"Topics may have many partitions, so it can handle an arbitrary amount of data."
3) Partition offset
Each partitioned message has a unique sequence id called as offset.
4) Replicas of partition
Replicas are nothing but backups of a partition. Replicas are never read or write data. They are
used to prevent data loss.
5) Brokers
Brokers are a simple system responsible for maintaining the pub-lished data. Each broker may
"have zero or more partitions per topic. Assume, if there are N partitions in a topic and N number of brokers, each broker will have one partition."
"Assume if there are N partitions in a topic and more than N brokers (n + m), the first N broker"
will have one partition and the next M broker will not have any partition for that particular topic.
"Assume if there are N partitions in a topic and less than N brokers (n-m), each broker will have"
one or more partitions shared among them. This scenario is not recommended due to unequal load distri-bution among the broker.
6) Kafka Cluster
Kafka’s having more than one broker is called the Kafka cluster. A Kafka cluster can be
expanded without downtime. These clusters are used to manage the persistence and replication of message data.
7) Producers
Producers are the publisher of messages to one or more Kafka topics. Producers send data to
"Kafka brokers. Every time a producer pub-lishes a message to a broker, the broker simply appends the message to the last segment file. Actually, the message will be appended to a"
partition. Producers can also send messages to a partition of their choice.
8) Consumers
Consumers read data from brokers. Consumers subscribe to one or more topics and consume
published messages by pulling data from the brokers.
9) Leader
Leader is the node responsible for all reads and writes for the given partition. Every partition has
one server acting as a leader.
10) Follower
"Nodes which follow leader instructions are called followers. If the leader fails, one of the"
"followers will automatically become the new leader. A follower acts as a normal consumer, pulls messages and updates its own data store."
Apache Kafka - Cluster Architecture
The following table describes each of the components shown in the above diagram.
1) Broker
"Kafka cluster typically consists of multiple brokers to maintain load balance. Kafka brokers are stateless, so they use ZooKeeper for maintaining their cluster state. One Kafka broker instance can handle hundreds of thousands of reads and writes per second and each bro-ker can handle TB of messages without performance impact. Kafka broker leader election can be done by"
ZooKeeper.
2) ZooKeeper
ZooKeeper is used for managing and coordinating Kafka broker. ZooKeeper service is mainly used to notify producer and consumer about the presence of any new broker in the Kafka system or failure of the broker in the Kafka system. As per the notification received by the
Zookeeper regarding presence or failure of the broker then pro-ducer and consumer takes
decision and starts coordinating their task with some other broker.
3) Producers
"Producers push data to brokers. When the new broker is started, all the producers search it and automatically send a message to that new broker. Kafka producer doesn’t wait for acknowledgements from the broker and sends messages as fast as the broker can handle."
4) Consumers
"Since Kafka brokers are stateless, which means that the consumer has to maintain how many messages have been consumed by using partition offset. If the consumer acknowledges a particular message offset, it implies that the consumer has consumed all prior messages. The consumer issues an asynchronous pull request to the broker to have a buffer of bytes ready to consume. The consumers can rewind or skip to any point in a partition simply by supplying an"
offset value. Consumer offset value is notified by ZooKeeper
Kafka Installation on Ubuntu 20.04
Reference link used for kafka_installations
To install kafka we need the dependencies of java jdk files
sudo apt install openjdk-11-jdk
To check version
java -version
To install the latest kafka visit the link and download binary files
Binary files are highlighted below for reference
wget https://downloads.apache.org/kafka/3.5.1/kafka_2.12-3.5.1.tgz
To extract the .tgz file
sudo tar xvf kafka_2.12-3.5.1.tgz
To Change the file name as kafka we use the below command
mv kafka_2.12-3.5.1.tgz kafka
To move the entire files to opt dir
mv kafka /opt/
To run the zookeeper as service we need to write the below zookeeper
service file in systemd location
sudo nano /etc/systemd/system/zookeeper.service
[Unit]
Description =Apache Zookeeper service Requires=network.target remote-fs.target After=network.target remote-fs.target [Service]
Type=simple
ExecStart=/opt/kafka/bin/zookeeper-server-start.sh /opt/kafka/config/zookeeper.properties ExecStop=/opt/kafka/bin/zookeeper-server-stop.sh
Restart=on-abnormal [Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target
To reload the daemon we use the below command
sudo systemctl daemon-reload
To run the kafka as service we need to write the below kafka service file in
systemd location
sudo nano /etc/systemd/system/kafka.service
[Unit]
Description =Apache kafka service Requires=zookeeper.service After=network.target remote-fs.target [Service]
Type=simple
"#Environment =""JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib/jvm/java-11-openjdk-11-jdk-amd64"" ExecStart=/opt/kafka/bin/kafka-server-start.sh /opt/kafka/config/server.properties ExecStop=/opt/kafka/bin/kafka-server-stop.sh"
[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target
To reload the daemon we use the below command
sudo systemctl daemon-reload
To Start the zookeeper service we use the below command
sudo systemctl start zookeeper
To check the status of zookeeper service we use the below command
sudo systemctl status zookeeper
To Start the kafka service we use the below command
sudo systemctl start kafka
To check the status of kafka service we use the below command
sudo systemctl status kafka
For creating a first topic in kafka we use the below command
sudo bin/kafka-topics.sh --create --topic test --bootstrap-server localhost:9092 --replication-
factor 1 --partitions 4
To Check the list of topics created .
sudo bin/kafka-topics.sh --list --bootstrap-server localhost:9092
To send some messages for created Topic
sudo bin/kafka-console-producer.sh --broker-list localhost:9092 --topic test
type messages and enter ctrl+z
use the below command to see list of messages
sudo bin/kafka-console-consumer.sh --bootstrap-server localhost:9092 --topic test --from-
beginning
