Mysql Server to Sql server Migration
Installing ms-sql server
https://adamtheautomator.com/microsoft-sql-server-standard-edition/
a)  We have .sql dump file with mysqldump from mysql server and we have to
Load this file to SQL server (MicroSoft sql server)
Pre-requisites : -
1)   Connector/ODB
https://dev.mysql.com/downloads/connector/odbc/
2)  MySQL to SQL Server assistance
https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=54257
3)  If you are unable to access that particular mysql server and you are having a dump file
please install mysql server on your windows system and execute that .sql files there and itself.
Now open the MySQL to SQL Server assistance application and connect to both mysql and sql
server here using credentials.
Assess
"By using SSMA for MySQL, you can review database objects and data and assess databases"
for migration.
To create an assessment:
1)  Open SSMA for MySQL.
"2)  On the File menu, select New Project."
3)  Enter the project name and a location to save your project and the migration target.
Then select SQL Server in the Migrate To option.
"4) In the Connect to MySQL dialog box, enter connection details, and then connect to your"
MySQL server.
5) Select the MySQL databases you want to migrate.
"6) Right-click the MySQL database in MySQL Metadata Explorer, and select Create Report."
"Alternatively, you can select the Create Report tab in the upper-right corner."
7) Review the HTML report to understand conversion statistics and any errors or warnings. You
can also open the report in Excel to get an inventory of MySQL objects and the effort required to
"perform schema conversions. The default location for the report is in the report folder within SSMAProjects, as shown here:"
drive:\Users\<username>\Documents\SSMAProjects\MySQLMigration\report\report_2016_11_1
2T02_47_55\.
Validate the type mappings
"Validate the default data type mappings and change them based on requirements, if necessary."
To do so:
"1) On the Tools menu, select Project Settings."
2) Select the Type Mapping tab.
3) You can change the type mapping for each table by selecting the table in MySQL Metadata
Explorer.
"To learn more about conversion settings in SSMA for MySQL, see Project Settings."
Convert the schema
"Converting database objects takes the object definitions from MySQL, converts them to similar"
"SQL Server objects, and then loads this information into the SSMA for MySQL metadata. It doesn't load the information into the instance of SQL Server. You can then view the objects and their properties by using SQL Server Metadata Explorer."
"During the conversion, SSMA for MySQL prints output messages to the output pane and error"
messages to the Error List pane. Use the output and error information to determine whether you have to modify your MySQL databases or your conversion process to obtain the desired
conversion results.
To convert the schema:
"1) (Optional) To convert dynamic or ad hoc queries, right-click the node and select Add"
Statement.
2) Select the Connect to SQL Server tab.
a)Enter connection details for your SQL Server instance.
"b)Select your target database from the drop-down list, or enter a new name, in which case a database will be created on the target server."
"c)Enter authentication details, and then select Connect."
"3) Right-click the MySQL database in MySQL Metadata Explorer, and then select Convert"
"Schema. Alternatively, you can select the Convert Schema tab in the upper-right corner."
"4)  After the conversion finishes, compare and review the converted objects to the original"
objects to identify potential problems and address them based on the recommendations.
"5)  Compare the converted Transact-SQL text to the original code, and review the"
recommendations.
"6)  In the output pane, select Review results and review the errors in the Error List pane."
"7)  Save the project locally for an offline schema remediation exercise. On the File menu,"
select Save Project. This step gives you an opportunity to evaluate the source and target schemas offline and perform remediation before you publish the schema to SQL Server.
Migration
After you have the necessary prerequisites in place and have completed the tasks associated
"with the pre-migration stage, you're ready to perform the schema and data migration."
You have two options for migrating data:
Client-side data migration
"To perform client-side data migration, select the Client Side Data Migration Engine option in the"
Project Settings dialog box.
 Note
"When SQL Express edition is used as the target database, only client-side data migration is  allowed and server-side data migration isn't supported."
Server-side data migration
"Before you perform data migration on the server side, ensure that:"
The SSMA for MySQL Extension Pack is installed on the instance of SQL Server. The SQL Server Agent service is running on the instance of SQL Server.
"To perform server-side data migration, select the Server Side Data Migration Engine option in the Project Settings dialog box."
Important
"If you plan to use the Server Side Data Migration Engine, before you migrate data, you must"
"install the SSMA for MySQL Extension Pack and the MySQL providers on the computer that's running SSMA for MySQL. The SQL Server Agent service must also be running. For more information about how to install the extension pack, see  Installing SQL Server Migration"
Assistant Components on SQL Server (MySQL to SQL)
To publish your schema and migrate the data:
1) Publish the schema by right-clicking the database in SQL Server Metadata Explorer and
selecting Synchronize with Database. This action publishes the MySQL database to the SQL Server instance.
2) Review the mapping between your source project and your target.
3) Migrate the data by right-clicking the database or object you want to migrate in MySQL
"Metadata Explorer and selecting Migrate Data. Alternatively, you can select the Migrate Data tab. To migrate data for an entire database, select the check box next to the database name. To migrate data from individual tables, expand the database, expand Tables, and then select the checkboxes next to the tables. To omit data from individual tables, clear the check boxes."
"4) After migration is completed, view the Data Migration Report."
"5) Connect to your SQL Server instance by using SQL Server Management Studio, and validate"
the migration by reviewing the data and schema.
Post-migration
"After you've successfully completed the migration stage, you need to complete a series of post-"
migration tasks to ensure that everything is functioning as smoothly and efficiently as possible.
Remediate applications
"After you've migrated the data to the target environment, all the applications that formerly"
consumed the source need to start consuming the target. Accomplishing this task will require changes to the applications in some cases.
For your reference:
https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/sql-server/migrate/guides/mysql-to-sql-
server?source=recommendations&view=sql-server-ver16
B) Restore .bak file to sql server
Prerequisites:
When we are doing these process the .bak from our should be in c drive
Path:- C:/programfile/microsoftserver/…../Backups
1. Restore .BAK to SQL Server via SQL Server Management Studio
Follow the below steps to restore a .bak file with SQL Server Management Studio:
"Step 1. Open SSMS (SQL Server Management Studio), right-click on the database"
"where you want to restore the .bak data to and select ""Tasks"" > ""Restore"" > ""Database""."
"Step 2. Click the three dots button next to the ""From device"" section, browse to"
choose the .bak file saved on your local drive.
"Step 3. Click ""Add"" to specify the exact location where you saved the .bak file,"
"select it and click ""OK"" to confirm."
"Step 4. Tick ""Full Database Backup"" and ""Transaction Log Backup"", click ""OK"""
to confirm.
"When the restore process completes, click ""OK"" to finish."
"Note: If the .bak file contains the backup of your SQL database, the whole"
process also works to restore your corrupted SQL Server database from
backup.
https://www.easeus.com/sql-database-recovery/3-ways-to-open-sql-bak-file-
in-excel.html#2
Network Issues -related
https://appuals.com/how-to-fix-the-error-a-network-related-or-instance-specific-error-occurred-
while-establishing-a-connection-to-sql-server/
