Instlling tomcat _9 version on ubuntu -20.04
"Step 1 – Install JAVA1) First, install OpenJDK 11. It is an implementation of the Java Platform. To update the pa"
"2) After installation, verify it by checking the version of JAVA.     java -versio"
"3) You'll get an output like this:   Output :   openjdk version ""11.0.7"" 2020-04-14OpenJDK Runtime Enviro Step 2 – Create Tomcat User and Group1) Create a new system user and group with a home directory of /opt/ Step 3 – Download Tomcat1) Check the Tomcat download page to see if a newer version is available."
"2) After that, use wget to download the Tomcat zip file to the /tmp directory:     VERSION=9.0.71wget http"
"3) After downloading, extract the tar file to /opt/tomcat directory.     sudo tar -xf /tmp/apache-tomcat-${VERSIO"
"4) Tomcat is typically updated regularly for security and to introduce new features. For more control, create a sym"
"5) Unpack the latest version, then update the symlink to point to it. Additionally, change the directory ownership t"
"6) After that, the shell scripts in Tomcat's bin directory need to be made executable.     sudo sh -c 'chmod +x /o"
Step 4 – Create the SystemD Unit Fil e1) Open the text editor and create a tomcat.service unit file in the /etc
"2) After that, paste the following configuration in /etc/systemd/system/tomcat.service:    /etc/systemd/sys"
"3) Then, save and close the file. Notify systemd that a new file exists.     sudo systemctl daemon-reload"
"4) Once done, enable the Tomcat service and start it.     sudo systemctl enable --now tomcat"
5) You will need to check the service status.     sudo systemctl status tomcat
6) The result indicates that the Tomcat server is enabled and operational.     Output : tomcat.service - Tomcat 9
"7) Now you can start, stop, even restart Tomcat as any other systemd service. Use the following command:     s Step 5 – Configure the Firewall (Optional)If you wish to access Tomcat from outside the local network, you mu Step 6 – Configure the Tomcat Web Management InterfaceTo gain access to the Web Management Interfac"
2) Create a user with both admin-gui and manager-gui roles. This will enable access to the /host-manager/html
3) Open the tomcat-users.xml file. Create a new user with the following command:    sudo nano /opt/tomcat/la
"4) To increase security, change your username and password."
"5) To access the web interface from a remote IP, remove the restrictions. However, this is not recommended for You must enable access to the web interface from any location. To do this, open the following two files and comm"
"Step 7 – Testing the Tomcat Installation1) Proceed to open the browser, then type http://<your_domain_or_IP"
 SSL                                                                                                                                                                                              
"Quick StartThe description below uses the variable name $CATALINA_BASE to refer the base directory against Introduction to SSL/TLS  Transport Layer Security (TLS) and its predecessor, Secure Sockets Layer (SSL), ar ConfigurationPrepare the Certificate Keystore  Tomcat currently operates only on JKS, PKCS11 or PKCS12 For more advanced cases, consult the OpenSSL documentation.To create a new JKS keystore from scratch, co This command will create a new file, in the home directory of the user under which you run it, named "".keystore"". Edit the Tomcat Configuration FileTomcat can use two different implementations of SSL:        the JSSE implem To define a Java (JSSE) connector, regardless of whether the APR library is loaded or not, use one of the Alternatively, to specify an APR connector (the APR library must be available) use:   <!-- Define an HTTP/1 Importing the Certificate"
"Now that you have your Certificate you can import it into you local keystore. First of all you have to import a so ca Import the Chain Certificate into your keystorekeytool -import -alias root -keystore <your_keystore_filename> Using OCSP Certificates  To use Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP) with Apache Tomcat, ensure you h Create a private key:openssl genrsa -aes256 -out ocsp-cert.key 4096Create a signing request (CSR):ope"
sample command to import certificate from another keystorekeytool -importkeystore -srckeystore tom
"ckages index and install the OpenJDK 11 JDK package, run the following commands:   sudo apt updatesudo"
nment (build 11.0.7+10-post-Ubuntu-3ubuntu1)OpenJDK 64-Bit Server VM (build 11.0.7+10-post-Ubuntu-3ubun
tomcat to run the Tomcat service. Enter the following command:        sudo useradd -m -U -d /opt/tomcat -s /
s://downloads.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-9/v${VERSION}/bin/apache-tomcat-${VERSION}.tar.g
N}.tar.gz -C /opt/tomcat/
"bolic link called ""latest"" that points to the Tomcat installation directory.   sudo ln -s /opt/tomcat/apache-tomc"
o the user and group tomcat using:     sudo chown -R tomcat: /opt/tomcat
"pt/tomcat/latest/bin/*.sh'  These scripts are useful for starting, stopping, and managing Tomcat instances."
/systemd/system/ directory.     sudo nano /etc/systemd/system/tomcat.servic
tem/tomcat.service[Unit]Description=Tomcat 9 servlet containerAfter=network.target[Service]Type=forkingUser
servlet containerLoaded: loaded (/etc/systemd/system/tomcat.service; enabled; vendor preset: enabled)Active
udo systemctl start tomcatsudo systemctl stop tomcatsudo systemctl restart tomcat
"st open port 8080. To do so, use the following command:     sudo ufw allow 8080/tcp  ⚠฀While running Tom e, you must create a user.1) Navigate to the tomcat-users.xml file, as this is where Tomcat users and roles are URL and allow for the creation, deletion, and management of virtual hosts. The manager-gui will also let you de"
"test/conf/tomcat-users.xml<tomcat-users><!--Comments--><role    rolename=""admin-gui""/><role    rolena"
"production systems, as it may have security implications."
ent out or remove the following lines:For Manager app:        sudo nano /opt/tomcat/latest/webapps/manag
_address>:8080. Change your_domain_or_IP_address.The screen will look like this:Apache Tomcat
which most relative paths are resolved. If you have not configured Tomcat for multiple instances by setting a C
"e technologies which allow web browsers and web servers to communicate over a secured connection. This m format keystores. The JKS format is Java's standard ""Java KeyStore"" format, and is the format created by the ntaining a single self-signed Certificate, execute the following from a terminal command line:        Unix:$JAVA_ To specify a different location or filename, add the -keystore parameter, followed by the complete pathname to entation provided as part of the Java runtime (since 1.4)the APR implementation, which uses the Open following:   <!-- Define an HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 8443, JSSE NIO implementation --><Connector prot"
".1 Connector on port 8443, APR implementation --><Connector protocol=""org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11Apr"
lled Chain Certificate or Root Certificate into your keystore. After that you can proceed with importing your Cert
"-trustcacerts -file <filename_of_the_chain_certificate>And finally import your new Certificatekeytool -import - ave downloaded, installed, and configured the Tomcat Native Connector. Furthermore, if you use the Windows nssl req -config openssl.cnf -new -sha256 \ -key ocsp-cert.key -out ocsp-cert.csrSign the CSR:openssl cat.keystore -destkeystore tomcatkey.p12 -detstoretype PKCS12 -storepass zon@123     keytool = tool c"
apt install openjdk-11-jdk
"tu1, mixed mode, sharin"
bin/false tomcat
at-${VERSION} /opt/tomcat/latest
"=tomcatGroup=tomcatEnvironment=""JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib/jvm/java-11-openjdk-amd64""Environment=""JAVA_"
: active (running) since Tue 2020-05-12 17:58:37 UTC; 4s agoProcess: 5342 ExecStart=/opt/tomcat/latest/bin/
"cat in a production environment, use the load balancer, or reverse proxy. It is a best practice to allow access to"
defined.
ploy and undeploy web-applications without needing to restart the entire container through the /host-manager/h
"me=""manager-gui""/><user username=""admin"" password=""admin_password"" roles=""admin-gui,manage"
er/META-INF/context.xmlFor Host Manager app:sudo nano /opt/tomcat/latest/webapps/host-manager/META-
"ATALINA_BASE directory, then $CATALINA_BASE will be set to the value of $CATALINA_HOME, the director"
"eans that the data being sent is encrypted by one side, transmitted, then decrypted by the other side before pro keytool command-line utility. This tool is included in the JDK. The PKCS12 format is an internet standard, and c HOME/bin/keytool -genkey -alias tomcat -keyalg RSA      (The RSA algorithm should be preferred as a se your keystore file, to the keytool command shown above. You will also need to reflect this new location in the s SSL engine by default. The exact configuration details depend on which implementation is being used. If you ocol=""org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11NioProtocol"" port=""8443"" .../><!-- Define a HTTP/1.1 Connector on Protocol""          port=""8443"" .../>If you are using APR, you have the option of configuring an alternative engine"
ificate.Download a Chain Certificate from the Certificate Authority you obtained the Certificate from.For Verisig
"alias tomcat -keystore <your_keystore_filename>   -file <your_certificate_filename>Each Certificate Authority t platform, ensure you download the ocsp-enabled connector.To use OCSP, you require the following:OCSP-ena ca -openssl.cnf -extensions ocsp -days 375 -notext \ -md sha256 -in ocsp-cert.csr -out ocsp-cert.crtYo ommandimportkeystore = Imports one or all entries from another keystoresrckeystore = source keystore namet"
"OPTS=-Djava.security.egd=file:///dev/urandom        -Djava.awt.headless=true""Environment=""CATALINA_BASE=/op"
"startup.sh (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)Main PID: 5362 (java)"
"port 8080, only from the internal network."
tml interface.
"r-gui""/></tomcat-users>"
"INF/context.xml<ContextantiResourceLocking=""false"" privileged=""true"" >. . .<!--<Valve className=""org.apach"
"y into which you have installed Tomcat.To install and configure SSL/TLS support on Tomcat, you need to follow"
"cessing. This is a two-way process, meaning that both the server AND the browser encrypt all traffic before se an be manipulated via (among other things) OpenSSL and Microsoft's Key-Manager.Each entry in a keystore i cure algorithm, and this also ensures general compatibility with other servers and components.)"
"erver.xml configuration file, as described later. For example:Unix: $JAVA_HOME/bin/keytool -genkey configured Connector by specifying generic protocol=""HTTP/1.1"" then the implementation used by Tomcat is port 8443, JSSE BIO implementation --><Connector protocol=""org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11Protocol"""
"to OpenSSL.<Listener className=""org.apache.catalina.core.AprLifecycleListener""        SSLEngine=""someen"
n.com commercial certificates go to: http://www.verisign.com/support/install/intermediate.htmlFor Verisign.com
ends to differ slightly from the others. They may require slightly different information and/or provide the certifica bled certificatesTomcat with SSL APR connectorConfigured OCSP responderGenerating OCSP-Enabled Certi   u may verify the certificate:openssl x509 -noout -text -in ocsp-cert.crt     Configuring OCSP omcat.keystore = name of keystoredestkeystore = destination keystore nametomcatkey.p12 = name of the des
"t/tomcat/latest""Environment=""CATALINA_HOME=/opt/tomcat/latest""Environment=""CATALINA_PID=/opt/tomca"
"e.catalina.valves.RemoteAddrValve""allow=""127\.\d+\.\d+\.\d+|::1|0:0:0:0:0:0:0:1"" />-->. . .</Context>If you want"
"these simple steps. For more information, read the rest of this HOW-TO.Create a keystore file to store the serv"
"nding out data.Another important aspect of the SSL/TLS protocol is Authentication. This means that during your s identified by an alias string. Whilst many keystore implementations treat aliases in a case insensitive manner,"
"-alias tomcat -keyalg RSA -keystore /path/to/my/keystore  After executing this command, you will first be"
"chosen automatically. If the installation uses APR - i.e. you have installed the Tomcat native library - then it will u port=""8443"" .../>"
"gine"" SSLRandomSeed=""somedevice"" />The default value is<Listener className=""org.apache.catalina.core.A"
trial certificates go to: http://www.verisign.com/support/verisign-intermediate-ca/Trial_Secure_Server_Root/inde
"te and associated certificate chain in different formats. Additionally, the rules that the Certificate Authorities use ficatesApache Tomcat requires the OCSP-enabled certificate to have the OCSP responder location encoded in Connector To configure the OCSP connector, first verify that you are loading the Tomcat APR library. C tination keystore namedetstoretype = destination keystore formatPKCS12 = format keystorestorepasswd =Cha"
"t/latest/temp/tomcat.pid""Environment=""CATALINA_OPTS=-Xms512M -Xmx1024M -server -XX:+UseParallelGC"
"to restrict access to the web interface to a specific IP, add the address to the list.Use | to separate the IP addre"
er's private key and self-signed certificate by executing the following command:                   Unix:$JAVA_HO
"initial attempt to communicate with a web server over a secure connection, that server will present your web b case sensitive implementations are available. The PKCS11 specification, for example, requires that aliases ar"
"prompted for the keystore password. The default password used by Tomcat is ""changeit"" (all lower case), altho"
"se the APR SSL implementation, otherwise it will use the Java JSSE implementation.As configuration attribute"
"prLifecycleListener""         SSLEngine=""on"" SSLRandomSeed=""builtin"" />So to use SSL under APR, make sur"
x.htmlFor Trustcenter.de go to: http://www.trustcenter.de/certservices/cacerts/en/en.htm#serverFor Thawte.co
for issuing certifcates change over time. As a result you may find that the commands given above may need t the certificate. The basic OCSP-related certificate authority settings in the openssl.cnf file could look as follow heck the Apache Portable Runtime (APR) based Native library for Tomcat for more information about i nges the store password of a keystorezon@123 = passwd
"""ExecStart=/opt/tomcat/latest/bin/startup.shExecStop=/opt/tomcat/latest/bin/shutdown.sh[Install]WantedBy=m"
"sses in the list. You can add a single IP address or can also use a regular expression.After that, restart the Tom"
"ME/bin/keytool -genkey -alias tomcat -keyalg RSA          and specify a password value of ""changeit"".Uncom"
"rowser with a set of credentials, in the form of a ""Certificate"", as proof the site is who and what it claims to be. I e case sensitive. To avoid issues related to the case sensitivity of aliases, it is not recommended to use aliases"
ugh you can specify a custom password if you like. You will also need to specify the custom password in the se
"s for SSL support significantly differ between APR vs. JSSE implementations, it is recommended to avoid auto-"
e the SSLEngine attribute is set to something other than off. The default value is on and if you specify another v
m go to: http://www.thawte.com/certs/trustmap.html
o be modified. If you require assitance then help is available via the Apache Tomcat users mailing list.
s:#... omitted for brevity[x509]x509_extensions = v3_issued[v3_issued]subjectKeyIdentifier=hashauthorityKeyId
nstallation of APR. A basic OCSP-enabled connector definition in the server.xml file looks as follows:<C
"ulti-user.targetYou can modify the JAVA_HOME variable, if the path to Java installation is different."
cat service to apply the changes.
"ment the ""SSL HTTP/1.1 Connector"" entry in $CATALINA_BASE/conf/server.xml and modify as described in th"
"n certain cases, the server may also request a Certificate from your web browser, asking for proof that you are that differ only in case.To import an existing certificate into a JKS keystore, please read the documentation (in"
"rver.xml configuration file, as described later.Next, you will be prompted for general information about this Certi"
selection of implementation. It is done by specifying a classname in the protocol attribute of the Connector.
"alue, it has to be a valid engine name.SSLRandomSeed allows to specify a source of entropy. Productive syste"
"entifier=keyid,issuer# The address of your responderauthorityInfoAccess = OCSP;URI:http://127.0.0.1:8088ke"
"onnector port=""8443""  protocol=""org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11AprProtocol""  secure=""true"" schem"
e Configuration section below.
"who you claim to be. This is known aSs S""CLl/iTeLntSAaunthdeTnoticmactiaotn,""ItailsthiomupgohrtiannptrtaocnticoeteththisatiscounsefigdumrinogreTfoomr bcautsitnoet your JDK documentation package) about keytool. Note that OoppeennSsSsLl pokftcesn1a2d-desxpreoardta-ibnlemcyocmemrte.cnrtts-binekfoeryemth"
"ficate, such as company, contact name, and so on. This information will be displayed to users who attempt to a"
m needs a reliable source of entropy but entropy may need a lot of time to be collected therefore test systems
"yUsage    =    critical,digitalSignature,nonRepudiation,keyEncipherment,dataEncipherment,keyAgreement,keyCertS"
"e=""https""  SSLEnabled=""true"" SSLCertificateFile=""/path/to/ocsp-cert.crt""  SSLCertificateKeyFile=""/pa"
sask-etoa-bduvasinnteasgse(oBf2sBe)cturraenssaocctkioentssitshuasnuwailtlyh oinndlyivnidecessary when running it as a stand-alone web server. Detail
"yekkeeyy.k, ebyut keytool does n-oout st umpypcoertrtth.pa1t.2S-onaifmyeoutrocmecrtaiftic-aCtAe fhilaesmcoymCAm.ecnrtts befo"
-caname root -chai
"ccess a secure page in your application, so make sure that the information provided here matches what they w"
"could use no blocking entropy sources like ""/dev/urandom"" that will allow quicker starts of Tomcat.The final ste"
"ign,cRLSign,encipherOnly,decipherOnlybasicConstraints=critical,CA:FALS"
"th/to/ocsp-cert.key""  SSLCACertificateFile=""/path/to/ca.pem""  SSLVerifyClient=""require""  SSLVerifyDe"
s can be found in the Security Considerations Document. When running Tomcat primarily as a Servlet/JSP con
n
"ill expect.Finally, you will be prompted for the key password, which is the password specifically for this Certifica"
p is to con
"pth=""10""  clientAuth=""true""/>Starting OCSP Responder                                      Apache Tomcat will query"
"tainer behind another web server, such as Apache or Microsoft IIS, it is usually necessary to configure the prim"
te (as opposed to any other Certificates stored in the same keystore file). The keytool prompt will tell you that p
"an OCSP responder server to get the certificate status. When testing, an easy way to create an OCSP respon"
"ary web server to handle the SSL connections from users. Typically, this server will negotiate all SSL-related fu"
ressing the ENTER key automatically uses the same password for the key as the keystore. You are free to use
der is by executing the following:     openssl ocsp -port 127.0.0.1:8088 \   -text -sha256 -index index.txt \
"nctionality, then pass on any requests destined for the Tomcat container only after decrypting those requests. L"
the same password or to select a custom one. If you select a different password
-CA ca-chain.cert.pem -rkey ocsp-cert.key \   -rsigner ocsp-cert.crt          Do note that when using OCSP
"ikewise, Tomcat will return cleartext responses, that will be encrypted before being returned to the user's brows"
", the responder encoded in the connector certificate must be running. For further information, see OCSP docu"
"er. In this environment, Tomcat knows that communications between the primary web server and the client are"
mentation .
"taking place over a secure connection (because your application needs Ctoebrteifaicbaletetso aIsnkoardbeoruttothimis)p,lbeumteitndt oSe"
"SsLn, oatwpeabrtisceipravteer imn uthset heanvceryapntioanssoorcdiaetcerdypCtieorntifiticsaetlfe. for each external interface (IP address) that accepts secu"
re connections. The theory behind this design is that a server should provide some kind of reasonable assuran
"ce that its owner is who you think it is, particularly before receiving any sensitive information. While a broader e"
"xplanation of Certificates is beyond the scope of this document, think of a Certificate as a ""digital passport"" for"
"an Internet address. It states which organisation the site is associated with, along with some basic contact info"
"rmation about the site owner or administrator.This certificate is cryptographically signed by its owner, and is the"
refore extremely difficult for anyone else to forge. For the certificate to work in the visitors browsers without wa
"rnings, it needs to be signed by a trusted third party. These are called Certificate Authorities (CAs). To obtain a"
"signed certificate, you need to choose a CA and follow the instructions your chosen CA"
