Wincsp_user_based_setup
Requirements : -
1)  Creating one dedicated or hard-cored user with a home directory and no-login shell and also in
an optional directory also.
2)   Needed to create a specific group and these dedicated and individual users to specific group.
3)  One crontab with changing ownership of a specific directory is required to run for every few mins.
4)  Needed ownership of the dedicated user to that path otherwise he can not create files in subdirectories
5)  Needed to create one dummy tmp sub-directories.
Step -1 : Create SFTP User
I will create a sftp user (veera) for sftp restrict users to specific directory in Linux on server2.
"To create sftp user ""veera"", use the below command. Here we use -m to also create the user's home"
directory.
[root@server2 ~]# adduser veera
Check user details:
[root@server2 ~]# id veera
Output:
uid=1003(veera) gid=1003(veera) groups=1003(veera)
The user's home directory is owned by veera with 777 permissions so that no other user (other than
root) can access this directory.
Step 2: Create SFTP Group
"In this article to demonstrate sftp restrict users to specific directory, I will use sftp user instead of sftp"
group. But if you have a requirement to implement group level sftp chroot jail then you can also create sftp group using below steps:
"[root@server2 ~]# groupadd www-data  <-- Here group name is ""www-data"""
Add your user to this sftpusers group
"[root@server2 ~]# usermod --gid www-data veera <-- Adding user ""veera"" to group ""www-data"""
"Now you can use this group ""www-data"" to restrict users to a specific directory."
Step 3: Configure SFTP chroot jail
To configure SFTP chroot jail we will modify /etc/ssh/sshd_config
############### Group ##############################
[root@server2 ~]# nano /etc/ssh/sshd_config Subsystem      sftp   internal-sftp
"#Add this section to match for Group ""www-data"" Match Group www-data"
ChrootDirectory /var/www/vhosts/ X11Forwarding no AllowTcpForwarding no PermitTunnel no AllowAgentForwarding no
ForceCommand internal-sftp
######################## User Based #######################
Subsystem      sftp   internal-sftp
"#Add this section to match for Group ""www-data""  Match User Username"
ChrootDirectory /var/www/vhosts/  X11Forwarding no  AllowTcpForwarding no  PermitTunnel no  AllowAgentForwarding no
ForceCommand internal-sftp
#########################################
Match
"Introduces a conditional block. If all of the criteria on the Match line are satisfied, the keywords on the"
"following lines override those set in the global section of the config file, until either another Match line or the end of the file. If a keyword appears in multiple Match blocks that are satisfied, only the first"
instance of the keyword is applied.
ChrootDirectory
The ChrootDirectory must contain the necessary files and directories to support the user's session. For
"an interactive session this requires at least a shell, typically sh, and basic /dev nodes such as null, zero, stdin, stdout, stderr, and tty devices.For file transfer sessions using SFTP no additional configuration of the environment is necessary if the in-process sftp-server is used, though sessions"
which use logging may require /dev/log inside the chroot directory on some operating systems.
X11Forwarding
"This allows/denies the X11 forwarding. If set to yes, it can expose X11 to attacks; so this option must"
be taken with care. Defaults to no. We prevent the forwarding to X11: there is no need for it and it can expose the system.
AllowTcpForwarding
"This allows/denies TCP forwarding and can take as argument yes, all, no, or local and remote. The first"
"two options allow the forwarding, the third denies it, and the local allows local forwarding only; remote enables remote forwarding only. There is no shell or TCP forwarding for our example."
ForceCommand
Specifying a command of internal-sftp will force the use of an in-process SFTP server that requires no
support files when used with ChrootDirectory.
AllowAgentForwarding
"Defines whether ssh-agent forwarding is allowed or not. Defaults to yes to increase the security, and"
"since it is not really needed for an sftp account, so we are going to disable it."
PermitTunnel
"This allows/denies the tunnel device forwarding. It takes yes, point-to-point , Ethernet, or no as"
"arguments. Yes enables both point-to-point and Ethernet forwarding. Defaults to no, and we want to be sure it is disabled since we do not need a tunnel for an sftp account."
SubSystem
The command sftp-server implements the SFTP file transfer subsystem.
Alternately the name internal-sftp implements an in-process SFTP server. This may simplify configurations using ChrootDirectory to force a different filesystem root on clients.
Why do we use internal-sftp instead of sftp-server for ChrootDirectory?
Collected from: OpenSSH: Difference between internal-sftp and sftp-server
●   Both sftp-server and internal-sftp are part of OpenSSH. sftp-server is a standalone binary.
"●   internal-sftp is just a configuration keyword that tells sshd to use SFTP server code built- into sshd, instead of running another process (typically the sftp-server)."
●   sftp-server is now redundant and is kept for backward compatibility.
●   The main advantage of internal-sftp is that it requires no support files when used with the ChrootDirectory directive.
●   Administrators may rely on a login shell configuration to prevent certain users from logging in.
"●   Switching to the internal-sftp would bypass the restriction, as the login shell is no longer involved."
"●   Using sftp-server binary (being a standalone process) you can use some hacks, like running the SFTP under sudo."
"●   For SSH-1 (if anyone is still using it), the Subsystem directive is not involved at all."
●   An SFTP client using SSH-1 tells the server explicitly what binary the server should run. So legacy SSH-1 SFTP clients have sftp-server names hard-coded.
Next restart sshd service to activate sftp chroot jail configuration.
[root@server2 ~]# service ssh restart
Update the root:www-data permission for /var/www/vhosts/vhostsproduction/ path
Step4 : Create a bash script for winscpuserupdate.sh and update the below lines in bash script.
#!/bin/bash
chmod 777 -R /var/www/vhosts/vhostsproduction/webhooks.ceipal.com/*
chown -R www-data:www-data /var/www/vhosts/vhostsproduction/webhooks.ceipal.com/*
Script to create New users to access that particular path with their permissions.
#!/bin/bash
"echo ""Enter user name here"" read"
useradd -m $REPLY
"echo ""username is $REPLY"""
usermod --gid www-data s --shell /bin/false $REPLY passwd $REPLY
grep $REPLY /etc/passwd mkdir -p path/$REPLY/us
Chown -R root:www-data path/$REPLY/us
#########################################################################
challenges of sftp user based access
1) Need to create individual users with a home directory with no-login shell and create these
user_name dir with specific path - bash scripting is already written.
2) Add these individual users to the SFTPUSERS group.- bash scripting is already written.
3) The dedicated user is hard-cored in the ssh_config file.
4) The files which are created or modified by an individual user will reflect in a hard-cored user directory.
5) We have to give that specific path with all privileges means “chmod 777” so that all the individual
users also can read and write these directories and files of those specific path.
6)The individual user can only read and write files but the ownership of the file/directory will be changed
to a specific user only.
This can be overcome setting up crontab for every few mins like example 5 min interval
*/5 * * * * bash script.sh
Cmd in that crontab script file  Chmod 777 -R /var/www/vhosts/
chown -R root:www-data /var/www/vhosts/
Questions :
1)  What is the exact ownership of the specific paths with directories?
Means these exact paths will have ownership of root and www-data only by default.
2)  These individual user’s should only read those files/directories of a specific path or both read and write?
Scope : -
Approach
Match Group www-data
We can add users to www-data group and these particular users can access all the domain paths with
chmod 775 permissions so that users in the www-data group can rwx files and directories.
Match User username
"Each individual user has only a single specific path and cannot have multiple paths, As the chroot"
directory is applicable only for a single path.
Note : -
If a user is needed to add multiple paths then that specific user is also added to the group.
Challenges
https://www.ittsystems.com/troubleshooting-sftp-permission-denied/#wbounce-modal
