Wincsp_user_based_setup		
Requirements : -		
1)  Creating one dedicated or hard-cored user with a home directory and no-login shell and also in		
an optional directory also.		
2)   Needed to create a specific group and these dedicated and individual users to specific group.		
3)  One crontab with changing ownership of a specific directory is required to run for every few mins.		
4)  Needed ownership of the dedicated user to that path otherwise he can not create files in subdirectories		
5)  Needed to create one dummy tmp sub-directories.		
Step -1 : Create SFTP User		
I will create a sftp user (veera) for sftp restrict users to specific directory in Linux on server2.		
"To create sftp user ""veera"", use the below command. Here we use -m to also create the user's home"		
directory.		
[root@server2 ~]# useradd -m veera		
Check user details:		
[root@server2 ~]# id veera		
Output:		
uid=1003(veera) gid=1003(veera) groups=1003(veera)		
The user's home directory is owned by veera with 700 permissions so that no other user (other than		
root) can access this directory.		
[root@server2 ~]# ls -ld /home/veera/		
Output:		
drwx------ 2 veera veera 4096 Mar 30 18:48 /home/veera/		
Assign password to sftp user veera:		
[root@server2 ~]# passwd veera Output:		
New password:		
Retype new password:		
passwd: all authentication tokens updated successfully.		
Change the shell of the sftp user to /bin/false instead of /bin/bash. Without a valid shell the sftp user will		
not be allowed to login.		
[root@server2 ~]# usermod --shell /bin/false veera		
Verify the user veera’s properties		
[root@server2 ~]# grep veera /etc/passwd		
Output :		
veera:x:1003:1003::/home/veera:/bin/false		
Step 2: Create SFTP Group		
"In this article to demonstrate sftp restrict users to specific directory, I will use sftp user instead of sftp"		
group. But if you have a requirement to implement group level sftp chroot jail then you can also create sftp group using below steps:		
"[root@server2 ~]# groupadd sftpusers  <-- Here group name is ""sftpusers"""		
Add your user to this sftpusers group		
"[root@server2 ~]# usermod --gid sftpusers veera <-- Adding user ""veera"" to group ""www-data"""		
"Now you can use this group ""www-data"" to restrict users to a specific directory."		
Step 3: Configure SFTP chroot jail		
To configure SFTP chroot jail we will modify /etc/ssh/sshd_config		
############### Group ##############################		
[root@server2 ~]# nano /etc/ssh/sshd_config Subsystem      sftp   internal-sftp		
"#Add this section to match for Group ""sftpusers"" Match Group sftpusers"		
ChrootDirectory /var/www/vhosts/		
X11Forwarding no AllowTcpForwarding no		
PermitTunnel no		
AllowAgentForwarding no ForceCommand internal-sftp		
######################## User Based #######################		
Subsystem      sftp   internal-sftp		
"#Add this section to match for Group ""www-data"" Match User Username"		
ChrootDirectory /var/www/vhosts/ X11Forwarding no AllowTcpForwarding no PermitTunnel no AllowAgentForwarding no		
ForceCommand internal-sftp		
#########################################		
Match		
"Introduces a conditional block. If all of the criteria on the Match line are satisfied, the keywords on the"		
"following lines override those set in the global section of the config file, until either another Match line or the end of the file. If a keyword appears in multiple Match blocks that are satisfied, only the first"		
instance of the keyword is applied.		
ChrootDirectory		
The ChrootDirectory must contain the necessary files and directories to support the user's session. For		
"an interactive session this requires at least a shell, typically sh, and basic /dev nodes such as null,"		
"zero, stdin, stdout, stderr, and tty devices.For file transfer sessions using SFTP no additional"		
"configuration of the environment is necessary if the in-process sftp-server is used, though sessions which use logging may require /dev/log inside the chroot directory on some operating systems."		
X11Forwarding		
"This allows/denies the X11 forwarding. If set to yes, it can expose X11 to attacks; so this option must"		
be taken with care. Defaults to no. We prevent the forwarding to X11: there is no need for it and it can expose the system.		
AllowTcpForwarding		
"This allows/denies TCP forwarding and can take as argument yes, all, no, or local and remote. The first"		
"two options allow the forwarding, the third denies it, and the local allows local forwarding only; remote enables remote forwarding only. There is no shell or TCP forwarding for our example."		
ForceCommand		
Specifying a command of internal-sftp will force the use of an in-process SFTP server that requires no		
support files when used with ChrootDirectory.		
AllowAgentForwarding		
"Defines whether ssh-agent forwarding is allowed or not. Defaults to yes to increase the security, and"		
"since it is not really needed for an sftp account, so we are going to disable it."		
PermitTunnel		
"This allows/denies the tunnel device forwarding. It takes yes, point-to-point , Ethernet, or no as"		
"arguments. Yes enables both point-to-point and Ethernet forwarding. Defaults to no, and we want to be sure it is disabled since we do not need a tunnel for an sftp account."		
SubSystem		
The command sftp-server implements the SFTP file transfer subsystem.		
Alternately the name internal-sftp implements an in-process SFTP server. This may simplify configurations using ChrootDirectory to force a different filesystem root on clients.		
Why do we use internal-sftp instead of sftp-server for ChrootDirectory?		
Collected from: OpenSSH: Difference between internal-sftp and sftp-server		
●   Both sftp-server and internal-sftp are part of OpenSSH. sftp-server is a standalone binary.		
"●   internal-sftp is just a configuration keyword that tells sshd to use SFTP server code built- into sshd, instead of running another process (typically the sftp-server)."		
●   sftp-server is now redundant and is kept for backward compatibility.		
●   The main advantage of internal-sftp is that it requires no support files when used with the ChrootDirectory directive.		
●   Administrators may rely on a login shell configuration to prevent certain users from logging in.		
"●   Switching to the internal-sftp would bypass the restriction, as the login shell is no longer involved."		
"●   Using sftp-server binary (being a standalone process) you can use some hacks, like running the SFTP under sudo."		
"●   For SSH-1 (if anyone is still using it), the Subsystem directive is not involved at all."		
●   An SFTP client using SSH-1 tells the server explicitly what binary the server should run. So legacy SSH-1 SFTP clients have sftp-server names hard-coded.		
Next restart sshd service to activate sftp chroot jail configuration.		
[root@server2 ~]# systemctl restart sshd		
THese process is to create new paths and give him		
Step 5: SFTP restrict user to specific directory (with password authentication)		
Step 5.1: Create sftp chroot jail directories		
If you wish to restrict the user home directory then you can ignore these steps and only use		
"/home/<user> as chroot jail. But to cover sftp restrict users to specific directory, we need a directory structure."		
In this article we will implement sftp chroot jail on /opt/sftp-jails/<username>/exchange		
[root@server2 ~]# mkdir -p /opt/sftp-jails/usernames		
Step 5.2: Assign permissions on chroot jail directories		
The permissions you assign to sftp chroot directory may vary based on your requirement. The		
"below is just for your reference to do a POC (Proof of Concept) on sftp restrict users to specific directory. You may get ""fatal: bad ownership or modes for chroot directory"" error in"		
/var/log/messages of the permissions on sftp chroot jail directories are not configured		
properly.		
Our sftp user deepak will login to /opt/sftp-jails/<username> using sftp		
[root@server2 ~]# ls -ld /opt/sftp-jails/ Output:		
drwxr-xr-x 3 root root 4096 Mar 30 18:29 /opt/sftp-jails/		
It is mandatory to have the user and group owner set to root:root with 755 permission for the chroot		
"directory provided in /etc/ssh/sshd_config. If you set any other permission, then chroot jail will fail."		
Users will have no write permission on /opt/sftp-jails/<username>. There is another directory		
"""exchange"" under /opt/sftp-jails/<username>/ where sftp user will perform write operation. [root@server2 ~]# ls -ld /opt/sftp-jails/veera/"		
Output :		
drwxr-xr-x 3 root root 4096 Mar 30 18:29 /opt/sftp-jails/veera/		
As you see the user directory is owned by root with 755 permission to allow user deepak to login and		
sftp restrict user to specific directory /opt/sftp-jails/deepak		
We will change user owner to deepak to allow him write in this sftp chroot jail directory		
[root@server2 ~]# chown veera : root /opt/sftp-jails/veera/us		
##########		
Also change the permission to 750 to restrict others from writing in this us directory.		
[root@server2 ~]# chmod 777 /opt/sftp-jails/veera/us		
Verify the permission:		
[root@server2 ~]# ls -ld /opt/sftp-jails/veera/us/ Output :		
drwxrwxrwx 2 veera root 4096 Mar 30 18:29 /opt/sftp-jails/veera/us/		
###########		
Below is the tree structure of the directories we have created to configure sftp restrict users to specific directory .		
[root@server2 ~]# tree -paug /opt/		
/opt/		
└── [drwxr-xr-x root    root   ] sftp-jails		
└── [drwxr-xr-x root    root   ] veera		
├── [drwxr-x--- veera  root   ] us		
We need to make the root user as owner for the home directory in order our user’s will be able		
to login to.		
# chown root:root /home/veera		
# chmod 0755 /home/veera		
"We will also create a new folder in the user’s home directory where it can upload, download and edit"		
"files for. Further we will set this user as owner for the directory and the group will be www-data, in which the user also named www-data is a member and is running the apache2 web server in Ubuntu."		
# mkdir /home/veera/web		
# chown -R veera:www-data /home/veera/us		
You can determine the user which is running the apache2 web server with the following command:		
# apachectl -S		
From now on the user is able to access its folder but without the option to break out from its		
home directory.		
Mount Web Root Directory to the Home Directory from the User		
"As we want to enable the user to upload, download and edit files within our web root directory,"		
we finally need to mount that web root directory to the user’s previously created home directory		
and here to the created web folder.		
In order that the user will be able to edit existing files and folders within the mounted web root		
"directory, we will execute the chown command again and this time recursive."		
# mount --bind /var/www/website /home/veera/us		
# chown -R veera:www-data /home/veera/us		
We will also ensure that new files and folders created in our folder web will inherit its group ID		
"(setgid), rather than the primary group ID of the user who created the file, and therefore will set as owner the sftpuser01 and the group www-data by using the chmod g+s command."		
chmod g+s /home/sftpuser01/web		
To remove the inheritance you have to execute the following command btw.		
# chmod g-s /home/sftpuser01/web The same for the user ID (setuid)		
"!!!!! can be configured on FreeBSD, other UNIX & Linux systems just ignore u+s !!!"		
# chmod u+s file		
"In case the web server apache2 needs to be able to write into some folders, you can permit"		
write access to these folders for apache2 as follows.		
# chmod g+w /home/veera/web/<Folder to be writable>		
"Further that the mount will still exist after a reboot, we also add it to the /etc/fstab file."		
#`		
/var/www/website /home/veera/us none bind 0 0		
#########################################################################		
Script to create New users to access that particular path with their permissions.		
#!/bin/bash		
"echo ""Enter user name here"" read"		
useradd -m $REPLY		
"echo ""username is $REPLY"""		
usermod --gid sftpusers --shell /bin/false $REPLY passwd $REPLY		
grep $REPLY /etc/passwd		
mkdir -p /opt/sftp-jails/$REPLY/us		
Chown -R root:www-data /opt/sftp-jails/$REPLY/us		
#########################################################################		
challenges of sftp user based access		
1) Need to create individual users with a home directory with no-login shell and create these		
user_name dir with specific path - bash scripting is already written.		
2) Add these individual users to the SFTPUSERS group.- bash scripting is already written.		
3) The dedicated user is hard-cored in the ssh_config file.		
4) The files which are created or modified by an individual user will reflect in a hard-cored user directory.		
5) We have to give that specific path with all privileges means “chmod 777” so that all the individual users also can read and write these directories and files of those specific path.		
6)The individual user can only read and write files but the ownership of the file/directory will be changed		
to a specific user only.		
This can be overcome setting up crontab for every few mins like example 5 min interval		
*/5 * * * * bash script.sh		
Cmd in that crontab script file		
Chmod 777 -R /opt/sftp-jails/veera/us/*		
chown -R veera:www-data /opt/sftp-jails/veera/us/*		
Questions :		
1)  What is the exact ownership of the specific paths with directories?		
Means these exact paths will have ownership of root and www-data only by default.		
2)  These individual user’s should only read those files/directories of a specific path or both read and write?		
Scope : -		
Approach		
Match Group www-data		
We can add users to www-data group and these particular users can access all the domain paths with		
chmod 775 permissions so that users in the www-data group can rwx files and directories.		
Match User username		
"Each individual user has only a single specific path and cannot have multiple paths, As the chroot"		
directory is applicable only for a single path.		
Note : -		
If a user is needed to add multiple paths then that specific user is also added to the group.		
Challenges		
https://www.ittsystems.com/troubleshooting-sftp-permission-denied/#wbounce-modal		
